在这个视频中，你的目标是了解一些扩散模型的基础知识。
In this video, your goal is to gain some intuition of diffusion models.
首先，我们将讨论扩散模型的目标，
First, we'll talk about the goal of the diffusion model,
然后我们将探讨如何利用你手中的各种游戏角色图片训练数据对这些模型有用，
then we'll talk through how the training data that you have of different sprites can be made useful to these models,
最后我们会讨论如何在这些数据上训练模型。
and then we'll talk about training the models themselves on this data.
那么，扩散模型的目标是什么呢？
What is the goal of diffusion models?
好吧，你有很多的训练数据，
Well, you have a lot of training data,
比如你在这里看到的视频游戏角色的图像。
such as these sprite images that you see down here of video game characters.
这就是你的训练数据集。
And this is your training dataset.
你想要的是更多在你的训练数据集中没有的角色图片。
And what you want is you want even more of these sprites that are not represented in your training dataset.
你可以使用一个神经网络，通过扩散模型过程为你生成更多这样的角色。
And you can use a neural network that can generate more of these sprites for you following the diffusion model process.
那么现在，我们如何让这些图像对神经网络有用呢？
So now, how do we make these images useful to the neural network?
嗯，你希望神经网络能够学习到游戏角色的一般概念，就是它是什么。
Well, you want the neural network to learn generally the concept of a sprite, what it is.
这可能是更细微的细节，比如，你知道，游戏角色的头发颜色或者它的腰带扣。
And that could be finer details, such as, you know, the hair color of the sprite or that it's wearing a buckle for its belt.
也可能是大概的轮廓，像头和身体的轮廓，以及所有在这之间的东西。
But it also could be general outlines, like of its head and body, and everything in between that.
有一种方法可以做到这一点，就是用你的数据强调细节或者大概轮廓。
And one way to do that, one way to kind of take your data and be able to emphasize either finer details
实际上，这就是在不同程度上添加噪声。
or general outlines is actually to add different levels of noise.
也就是对图像添加噪声，
So this is just adding noise to the image.
这被称为噪声过程。
And it's known as a noising process.
这其实是受物理学的启发。
And this is inspired by physics.
你可以想象一滴墨水滴入一杯水中。
You can imagine an ink drop into a glass of water.
一开始，你确切地知道墨水滴在哪里落下。
Initially, you know exactly where the ink drop landed.
但随着时间的推移，你会看到它在水中扩散，直到消失。
But over time, you actually see it diffuse into the water until it disappears.
这里的想法也是一样的，从Bob这个游戏角色开始，
And that's the same idea here, where you start with Bob the sprite,
当你添加噪声时，它会消失，直到你不知道它究竟是哪个游戏角色。
and as you add noise, it will disappear until you have no idea which sprite it actually was.
那么，当你逐渐给图像添加更多的噪声时，神经网络应该在每个噪声级别上想些什么呢？
And so what should the neural network really be thinking at each of these levels of noise when you add progressively more noise to the image?
嗯，当它是角色Bob的时候，你希望神经网络能说，
Well, when it's Bob the sprite, you want the neural network to say,
“对，这就是角色Bob！保持Bob的原样，
"Yeah, that's Bob the sprite, to keep Bob as is.
这是一个角色。”
That is a sprite."
如果它可能是Bob，如果它很可能是Bob，
If it's probably Bob, if it's likely to be Bob,
那么你可能希望神经网络能说：
then you probably want the neural network to say, you know,
“这上面有一些噪声。
"There's some noise on here.
建议可能的细节，使它看起来就像角色Bob。”
Suggest possible details to make it look just like Bob the sprite."
如果它现在只是一个角色的轮廓，
And if it's just an outline of a sprite now,
你只能感觉到这可能是一个角色人物，
here you can only get a sense that this is probably a sprite person,
但它可能是Bob，或者Fred，甚至可能是Nancy，
but it could be Bob or Fred or maybe even Nancy,
那么你就想要为可能的角色建议更普遍的细节。
then you want to suggest more general details for possible likely sprites.
所以，你可能会根据这个为Bob提供一些细节，
So maybe you'll suggest some details for Bob based on this,
或者你会为Fred提供一些细节。
or you'll suggest some details for Fred.
最后，如果你一点也不清楚，如果它看起来完全不像什么，
And finally, if you have no idea, if it looks like absolutely nothing,
你还是希望它更像一个游戏角色。
you still want it to look more like a sprite.
你仍然希望神经网络说：“你知道吗？
You still want the neural network to say, "You know what?
我仍然会拿这个完全有噪声的图像，
I'm going to still take this completely noisy image,
我会把它变成稍微像游戏角色一点的东西，
and I'm going to turn this into something that's slightly more sprite-like
我会提出一个游戏角色可能看起来的轮廓。”
by proposing an outline of what a sprite might look like."
好了，那么让我们看看这个添加噪声的过程，
All right, so let's take a look at what that noising process,
随着时间的推移，逐渐添加噪声的过程是什么样子的。
that process of adding noise progressively, looks like over time.
然后它就消失了，一滴墨水在一杯水里完全扩散开来。
And there it goes, an ink drop that's fully diffused in a glass of water.
那么现在让我们开始训练那个神经网络吧。
So now on to training that neural network.
它学会将不同的噪声图像变回游戏角色。
So it learns to take different noisy images and turn them back into sprites.
这就是你的目标。
That is your goal.
它是如何做到这一点的呢？它学会移除你添加的噪声，
And how it does that is it learns to remove the noise you added,
从完全没有主意的级别开始，那里只有纯粹的噪声，
starting with the no idea level, where it is just pure noise,
开始让人感觉可能有一个人在里面，
to starting to give a semblance of maybe there's a person in there,
看起来像Fred，然后最后是一个看起来像Fred的游戏角色。
to looking like Fred, and then finally a sprite that looks like Fred.
我想强调的是，没有主意的噪声级别非常重要，因为它是正态分布的。
And I just want to call out that the no idea level of noise is really important because it is normally distributed.
我的意思是，每一个像素都是从一个正态分布中抽样的，
And what I mean by that is each of those pixels is sampled from a normal distribution,
也被称为高斯分布或者钟形曲线。
also known as a Gaussian distribution or a bell-shaped curve.
所以当你想要让神经网络给你一个新的角色，比如这里的Fred，
So when you want to ask the neural network for a new sprite, such as Fred here,
你可以从那个正态分布中抽样噪声，
you can sample noise from that normal distribution,
然后你可以通过让神经网络逐渐移除那个噪声来得到一个全新的游戏角色。
and then you can get a completely new sprite by using the neural network to just remove that noise progressively.
所以现在你达到了你的目标：
So now you've reached your goal.
得到更多的、你没有训练过的游戏角色。
You can get even more sprites beyond all those that you had trained on.
在下一个视频中，我们将介绍抽样。
In the next video, we'll cover sampling.